<chapter id="sum.introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <sect1 id="sum.introduction.scope">
        <title>Scope</title>
        <para>This document is the software user manual (SUM) for the ICOL+ processor.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sum.introduction.objectives">
        <title>Objectives</title>
        <para>In images retrieved from spectrometers such as MERIS, an increase in the radiances,
            especially in the near infrared bands, can often be
            observed over water and in the vicinity of vegetated coasts. The affected area can extend over
            10km or even more. This increase is not (always) related to an increase in the aerosol optical
            depth but is caused by the so-called adjacency effect. This effect results when photons are reflected
            and scattered towards the sensor and where a substantial contrast exits between the target
            and its surrounding. During processing of such measurements the correction schemes need to take
            this effect into account, otherwise the increased radiance is erroneously associated with other
            physical processes, and the derived geophysical quantities have an increased error.
        </para>

        <para>Observations over waters near to land surfaces, both for coastal and inland waters, are affected
            because of the large contrast in the red and infrared part of the spectrum, where water is almost
            black and vegetated areas are very bright. The effect is easier to illustrate in coastal waters because
            it decreases from coastline to off-shore. This effect can best be studied in MERIS Full Resolution
            images, but even in reduced resolution the adjacency effect can also clearly be seen.
        </para>

        <para>
            In order to build up a reliable tool for the correction of the adjacency effect, the ICOL (= Improve
            Contrast over Ocean and Land) prototype processor was developed as BEAM plugin. Although this prototype
            (ICOL1.0) has
            proven to retrieve results as expected from theory, it has some well-known limitations:
            <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
                <listitem>
                    Restricted to coastal areas over water (although the AE is known to exist as well over land)
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    Restriction to case 1 waters
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    No proper handling of clouds and sea ice
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    Restricted to application on MERIS data only
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    Slow processing
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            To overcome these limitations and to be able to apply the AE correction within operational processing
            chains, an improved BEAM plugin (ICOL+) has been developed. With this processor, the AE correction is
            applicable
            anywhere over ocean as well as over land and considers case 2 waters, clouds and sea ice. An improved
            convolution scheme (the core mathematical part of the AE corection) has been integrated to significantly
            speed up the processor. Moreover, it is possible with ICOL+ to apply the AE correction on Landsat TM data.
            This feature mainly serves as a demonstration for the general portability of the AE correction scheme
            to other instruments within future projects (e.g. related to the Sentinel missions). However, the full
            correction scheme has been implemented as for MERIS and has shown to provide results as expected ([RD-2]).
        </para>

        <para>
            This manual basically describes and illustrates how to use the application. For a detailed description of
            the underlying algorithms see [RD-1], the technical realisation of the software package is outlined in
            [RD-3].
        </para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sum.introduction.readerLevel">
        <title>Reader Level</title>

        <para>
            This specification is mainly written for the following audiences:
            <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
                <listitem>
                    MERIS QWG members
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    Any other scientists interested in MERIS or Landsat TM image analysis
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            The ICOL user manual specifications assumes that the reader is familiar with basic concepts in
            using the BEAM software and its integrated processors.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sum.introduction.acronymsAndNomenclature">
        <title>Acronyms</title>

            <para>
                <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
                    <listitem>
                        AE - Adjacency Effect
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        AMORGOS - Accurate MERIS Ortho-Rectified Geo-location Operational Software
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        AOT - Aerosol Optical Thickness
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        ATBD - Algorithm Theoretical Basis Document
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        BC - Brockmann Consult
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        BEAM - Basic ERS &amp; Envisat (A)ATSR and Meris Toolbox
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        CTP - Cloud Top Pressure
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        DEM - Digital Elevation Model
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        ESA - European Space Agency
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        ESTEC - European Space Technology and Research Centre
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        FR - Full Resolution
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        FRG - Full Resolution Geo/Ortho-corrected
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        GPF - Graph Processing Framework
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        GPU - Graphics Processing Unit
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        ICOL - Improved Contrast over Ocean and Land
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        MERIS - Medium Resolution Imaging Spectrometer
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        NDSI - Normalized Difference Snow Index
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        NDVI - Normalized Difference Vegetation Index
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        QWG - Quality Working Group
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        RR - Reduced Resolution
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        RRG - Reduced Resolution Geo/Ortho-corrected
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        SoW - Statement of Work
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        SUM - Software User Manual
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        TM - Thematic Mapper
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        TOA - Top of Atmosphere
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        TS - Technical Specification
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        VVR - Verification and Validation Report
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sum.introduction.applicableDocuments">
        <title>Applicable Documents</title>

        <para>
            <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
                <listitem>
                    [AD-1] Development of a multi-mission adjacency effect correction for an operational implementation.
                    ESA Statement of Work GMES-CLVL-EOPG-SW-08-0003, Issue 1.4.
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    [AD-2] MERIS Level 2 Detailed Processing Model, PO-TN-MEL-GS-0006, 15 July 2009, Issue i8r0.
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sum.introduction.referenceDocuments">
        <title>Reference Documents</title>

        <para>
            <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
                <listitem>
                    [RD-1] ICOL+ ATBD. Version 1.0, ICOL+ project deliverable D4, 18 November 2010.
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    [RD-2] ICOL+ VVR. Version 1.0, ICOL+ project deliverable D8, 18 November 2010.
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    [RD-3] ICOL+ TS. Version 1.0, ICOL+ project deliverable D10, 18 November 2010.
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    [RD-4]  AMORGOS documentation: http://earth.esa.int/services/amorgos/download/
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    [RD-5]  Khronos Group OpenCL online documentation: http://www.khronos.org/opencl/
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    [RD-6]  USGS Earth Explorer data archive: http://edcsns17.cr.usgs.gov/EarthExplorer/
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
