<chapter id="sum.installation">
    <title>Software Installation</title>

    <sect1 id="sum.installation.plugin">
        <title>ICOL+ as BEAM plugin</title>
        <para>
            As a BEAM plugin, the ICOL+ processor needs the following software to be installed
            in advance:
            <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
                <listitem>
                    BEAM, version 4.8
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            The BEAM software can be obtained from the BEAM download page
            (www.brockmann-consult.de/beam).
        </para>

        <para>
            The ICOL+ software delivery consists of three jar files: the ICOL main module, an updated BEAM 4.8 GPF
            module containing ICOL relevant bug fixes,
            and the OpenCL modules, which provide additional Java classes which are optionally used by ICOL+
            for accelerating purpose in case that a proper GPU is installed in the computer:
            <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
                <listitem>
                    beam-meris-icol-2.5.jar
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    beam-gpf-4.8.1-SNAPSHOT.jar
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    opencl_jars.zip
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            The files beam-meris-icol-2.5.jar and beam-gpf-4.8.1-SNAPSHOT.jar need to be copied into the 'modules' folder of the BEAM
            installation (<xref linkend="figure.installation.beammodules" xrefstyle="select: label"/>).
            The opencl_jars.zip files needs to be unpacked into the 'lib' folder of the BEAM
            installation.
            Note that existing versions of BEAM and ICOL jar files (e.g. ICOL1.0) need to be replaced/overwritten to
            avoid version conflicts of Java classes. I.e., this is true for the file beam-gpf-4.8.jar.
        </para>

        <figure id="figure.installation.beammodules">
            <title>Installation of ICOL+ jar files in BEAM modules and lib folder (shown for Windows XP)</title>
            <graphic scale="40" fileref="figures/beammodules.png"/>
        </figure>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sum.installation.addons">
        <title>Additional Requirements</title>
        <para>
            To be able to process all options properly, the ICOL+ processor needs the following
            add-ons to be installed in BEAM (if not already done):
            <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
                <listitem>
                    MERIS L2 Auxdata module
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    GETASSE30 DEM (required for LANDSAT TM processing)
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    GETASSE30 DEM reader (required for LANDSAT TM processing)
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            The MERIS L2 Auxdata and the GETASSE30 DEM reader can be installed with the
            BEAM module manager. See BEAM help documentation for details
            (http://www.brockmann-consult.de/beam/doc/help/visat/ModuleManager.html).
            The GETASSE30 DEM can be downloaded from the BEAM download page. See also
            BEAM help documentation
            (http://www.brockmann-consult.de/beam/ doc/help/visat/GETASSE30ElevationModel.html).
        </para>
    </sect1>

    
</chapter>
